welcome back to 5-minute phase I'm dr.
Andy Galvan one of the main reasons I
make these videos is to help the average
everyday
even the high-level strength
conditioning professionals achieve their
athletes clients and personal goals and
one of the things I found over the years
that frustrates people the most is they
worked really really hard they do an
exercise that they absolutely hate and I
don't achieve their goals so today's
video I hope will clarify some of the
reasons why you might be failing and
missing your athletes or your own
personal goals and the first thing you
have to consider is a situation where
somebody says something like this hey I
want to get extra salt so I've got to do
why exercise a couple of easy examples I
want to lose some weight therefore I
have to start jogging or have to hit the
elliptical or swimming now if you've
seen any of my fat loss videos you know
my answer to all those but the same
thing could be happening on the other
news spectrum I want to get stronger
therefore I feel like I have to squat
there's no way to get more powerful
without doing box jumps and those
concepts while kind of true they're
actually fundamentally wrong we need to
learn to think about this at a much
larger scale because when in fact the
exercises themselves so the exercises
you choose to do don't determine the
outcome or the adaptation you get that's
actually more predicated on how you
extras execute the exercise itself it's
not the exercise you select but more
about how you execute it that matters so
if you look at this multiple choice
question I've developed for you and you
looked at the left hand side and I said
okay choose the correct answer you would
look at bicep curl and say okay that's
the exercise I pick to get hypertrophy
to get bigger arms and a snatch is what
I pick to get more powerful and a dead
left is for strength and ellipticals for
endurance while those are totally true
you can use a snatch to get more
powerful and you can definitely get
stronger with the deadlift it's not
fundamentally true that the exercise
itself determined the second column the
adaptation for example you could do a
bicep curl it definitely get bigger but
you could also use a bicep curl to
improve your endurance if you just did a
lot more repetitions of it you can also
it's funny to sort of think about I know
but use a
bicep curl for power if you did it light
and powerfully in fact the same can be
done on the end there in this spectrum
with the elliptical you can definitely
improve your endurance probably not
improve your strength very well unless
you're very weak but you could do it for
power if you just spritz it up the
elliptical a couple of steps if there's
no different than running stadium stairs
as long as you took some breaks in
between it recovered fully and made sure
you maximize power output so I'm hoping
we can expand the conversation about the
exercises we think we have to select to
get the adaptation of the outcome of the
result that we're looking for now I
think Cal Dietz does a very nice job of
explaining this I did a recent podcast
with him on barbell shrug you can check
out if you're not familiar with Cal's
work
he's the head strength conditioning
coach for the University of Minnesota
now when he does his cardio programs or
his workouts for his division 1 football
players he doesn't have them jog for a
half an hour that's gonna be really hard
for the 350-pound offensive linemen so
his cardio is still a 30-minute workout
but they do one repetition of the bench
press I'm 54 so their max strength one
repetition of the squat at 50% and they
just keep repeating that circuit so one
squat one bench one squat one bench and
they don't stop for 30 minutes
this elite shows a different exercise he
didn't choose a rower or a bike or the
pool or elliptical or anything like that
he used to been TAS want to get the same
adaptation on the end of the spectrum
you could be using something like box
squats or box jumps excuse me
and you may be getting more powerful but
you may also be saying I've been doing
box jumps for six months and I'm not
getting any more power I'm not jumping
any higher my vertical jump will ask
yourself how are you executing the Box
jump are you jumping up 35 times in a
row then you're not going to get more
powerful you have to be executing it
powerfully to get more power this means
like one repetition maybe two or three
take a break fully recover if you're
doing it 30 times in a row or as many
reps as you can do in five minutes
that's actually an endurance
sighs now it's no longer a power
exercise because you're jumping at such
a low relative power output to sustain
it over time
right so summarize what I mean here the
exercise itself does not determine the
adaptation it's the application how many
reps in a row how many steps did you do
what was your rest how heavy what was to
speed things like that actually
determine whether or not you improve
your speed power strength grow muscle
lose fat whatever
now the exercises themselves do have
some relevance of course so if I select
a bicep curl I can't expect to get
stronger my hamstring right so the
exercise that I select does regulate
things like the movement plane so what
I'm rotating this plane or moving in
this plane the muscles are the joints
that are being activated the contraction
type eccentric constant check isometric
it Texico proficiency
right so don't select an exercise that I
want somebody to do for maximum power if
they don't know how to do the exercise
they're clearly gonna have to compromise
speed or technique or safety to execute
the movement and we never want to do
that all right so the key point while
though the exercise selection is
important it doesn't solely select the
adaptation we're going to at you